You know what?
‏اسمعي‏
Visiting Beijing is no big deal.
الذهاب إلى بكين أمر بسيط
I just went there casually!
لقد ذهبنا
What's so special about it?
‫ما مدهش‬
Where have you been?
أين ذهبوا
We went to that...
ذهبنا إلى
When I was little, I got sick of visiting the Forbidden City, Tiananmen,
في طفولتي، في القصر الملكي، بوابة تيان آن
Wangfujing, the Yuanmingyuan Park, the Yihe Garden,
قصر الأمير   حديقة يوان مينغ   حديقة يي خه
and the Badaling Great Wall.
لقد سئمت من الذهاب إلى مدينة بادا
Locals don't even like going to those places.
لا يحب الناس بكين الذهاب إلى هذه الأماكن
Which places did you visit?
أين ذهبت؟
-Tell us where you've been. -Where have you been?
‏أخبريني، أين ذهبت؟‏
Beijing just has those scenic spots. The Forbidden City,
إنه مكان صغير في بكين
Tiananmen,
بوابة تيان آن
Wangfujing,
قصر الأمير
the Yihe Garden,
حديقة يي خه
and the Badaling Great Wall.
المدينة الطويلة في جبل بادا
What's the point of going there?
ما الذي يجب أن نذهب إليه؟
You didn't go, did you?
لم تذهب   لم تذهب
Bragger.
لا فائدة
Hey, if locals don't go, why should I?
‫ماذا أفعل إذا لم يذهب أحد
Then what did you do?
ماذا فعلت؟
I went to that school first.
سأذهب إلى تلك المدرسة
Their campus is huge,
إنه كبير في المدرسة
much better than ours.
أفضل بكثير من هنا
What's more,
ثم كنت هناك
I met a legendary figure there.
تعرفت على شخص أسطوري
-Who? -A legendary figure?
من هو الأسطوري
Their school's... that... that...
ذلك ذلك ذلك
Security guard.
حارس الأمن
What's so special about a security guard?
ما هو الحارس
Why do you look down on security guards?
لماذا لا تحترم الحارس
That guard's exceptionally capable.
‫إن الحارس قادر على القيام بالأعمال
-He's awesome. -That's all?
هذا كل شيء رائع
Anything else?
هل هناك المزيد؟
Yeah.
أيضا
Then we went to a mysterious alley.
ثم ذهبنا إلى زقاق غامض
They say there's an old lady in that alley.
‫قالت في الزقاق أن هناك عجوز‬
Whoever meets her gets their souls hooked away.
‫تم اختطاف من اصطدمه‬
I met her.
التقيت به
Judge Ma'am?
أيها القاضي
So basically, you just didn't go anywhere.
بصراحة، لم تذهب إلى أي مكان
What are you so smug about?
ما الذي جميل هنا؟
What do you mean, I didn't go anywhere?
ما معنى عدم الذهاب إلى أي مكان
I've been to a whole lot of places!
ذهبت إلى الكثير من الأماكن
-Well... -Then how did Xiaodan do on the exam?
ماذا عن اختبار شياو دان؟
What do you mean by "how she did"?
ماذا؟
Look at you.
أنت
So snobbish. Isn't the process important?
هل العملية مهمة؟
The process is more amazing, you know?
هذه العملية أجمل هل تعرف
Oh, no, sounds like she didn't pass the exam.
‫خلاص بعد قول هذا لم نجح في الامتحان‬
What are you talking about?
ماذا تقول
Look.
انظر
Xiaodan...
دان
X-Xiaodan.
شياو دان
Well.
هذا
Take a look.
انظر
See?
كيف
What did I say?
ماذا قلت
She didn't pass. She was just there enjoying the process.
‏لم اجتاز الامتحان‏
What's wrong with your class?
‏ما خطب صفك؟‏
I walked over from there,
‏أتيت من هناك‏
and your class is the only noisy one.
‏صفك فوضوي‏
What class is this? Where is the teacher?
ما هذا الدرس أين المعلم
Director Hou, Mr. Gu is sick.
سيد هو السيد قو مريض
We're having self-study this period.
سندرس هذا الفصل
Right.
‏أجل‏
Self-study.
الدراسة الذاتية
Do you know what "self-study" means?
‏هل تفهمين ما هو الدرس الذاتي؟‏
Class president, maintain some order.
‏يا قائدة الصف، نظّم النظام‏
Alright, alright.
‏حسناً‏
Go back to your seats. Go back.
ارجعوا للجلوس ارجعوا للجلوس
-Let's go back. -Class is starting.
عد إلى الصف
Xiaoman, Ms. Tong is sick,
شياو مان هل تعتقد أن السيد تونغ مريض
and Ms. Dai is also under the weather.
السيد داي ليس على ما يرام
Is there a flu going around our school?
هل يوجد زكام في مدرستنا
It's not the flu.
أي زكام؟
Don't you know?
‏ألا تعرفين؟‏
Our teachers were almost all
‏أساتذنا‏
taken out by the royal jelly from Xia Lei's family.
‫عصير نحل وانغ لعائلة شيا لي‬
What are you doing?
ماذا تفعل
Who are you throwing a tantrum at?
من ضربت؟
What am I doing? It's all because of this lousy royal jelly.
ماذا؟ هذا بسبب عصير النحل
It made all our teachers sick.
‏أسقط المعلّم‏
Now the whole grade's students are blaming me
الآن كل الصف يلومني
and this junk royal jelly our family makes.
‫قال إن منزلنا يصنع هذه العصير
Watch your tone with your mother!
كيف تتحدث مع والدتك
She works hard all day
أمك تعمل بجد في النهار متعبة جدا
and has to sell royal jelly when she gets home at night.
يجب أن تبيع معجون النحل في الليل
What for? Isn't it for your education?
من أجل ماذا؟ أليس من أجل استخدام الدراسة في المستقبل؟
To earn some money for our family!
لكسب بعض المال لعائلتنا
And here you are, yelling at us.
‫لماذا تصرخ
You sell this lousy royal jelly to make money?
لقد جنيت القليل من المال
It's a shoddy product.
منتجات منخفضة
Y-You're talking back to me now?
أنت أنت تقاوم معي
H-How was I supposed to know...
يمكنني أن أعرف
If I knew it was shoddy,
أريد أن أعرف أن جودتها منخفضة
would I... would I have stocked up on it? Honestly.
هل يمكنني الدخول
Your mother was scammed, too!
لقد خدعت والدتك
It's okay. D-Don't cry.
حسنا لا تبكي لا تبكي
You brat. We are victims, too!
نحن ضحايا أيضًا
Stop yapping!
‫لماذا تصرخ
Besides, we didn't sell many boxes.
علاوة على ذلك، لم تبيع الكثير من الصناديق
We've bought back the few we sold,
سنشتري جميع الصناديق التي بعتها
you know?
هل تعرف
Well...
هذا
What?
ماذا
Nothing. I... I was just asking.
لا شيء أنا فقط أسأل
Did you get your answer?
هل فهمت؟
Go! If you get it, go do your homework.
اذهب   إذا فهمت اذهب واكتب الواجبات
We'll call you for dinner.
سأتصل بك عند تناول الطعام
Mom, don't get upset.
أمي لا تغضبي
I-It's none of your business.
هذا ليس من شأنك
Stay o-out of this.
لا تهتم
Go, just go!
اذهب اذهب اذهب
Brat, how could you yell at your mother?
لقد ناديت والدتك
Was that okay, Honey?
هل هذا جيد يا زوجتي
Did I show enough authority
هل كنت قوياً
as the head of the family just now?
زعيم العائلة
Why were you so harsh with our son?
لماذا أنت عنيف مع الأطفال
Why were you so fierce?
لماذا أنت عنيف هكذا
H-He was yelling at you.
إنه يناديك
Okay, okay.
حسنا حسنا
Then I... I'll go apologize to him.
سأذهب لأعتذر له
That's not necessary.
لا داعي لذلك
Just watch it next time.
انتبه في المرة القادمة
Don't drink that.
لا تشرب
It'll be a waste.
هذا مضيعة
What if you get diarrhea?
ماذا لو أُصبت بالإسهال حقًا؟
That's like suicide.
هذا يعني الانتحار
It is a bit of a waste.
هذا مضيعة بعض الشيء
If we get sick, we get sick together.
إذا أردنا أن نسحب معا
Alright. It's okay.
حسنا حسنا
Let it go.
دع الأمر يمر
Oh, my...
حقا
Studying hard?
أنا أعمل بجد
What brings you here?
لماذا أنت هنا؟
Nothing really. Are your parents asleep?
لا بأس هل نام والداك
At this hour? Definitely.
بالتأكيد نام في هذا الوقت
The weather's nice today.
اليوم مريح جدا
Let me take you out for a walk
سآخذك للتجول
to clear your head.
لتغيير عقلك
Nice.
حسنا
Let's go.
لنذهب
Why don't you go to sleep at night?
لماذا لم تنامي في الليل
I don't want to.
لا أريد النوم
The plant is full of people during the day.
‫كل الناس في المصنع في النهار‬
Too noisy.
‫في المصنع‬
That is everyone's East Chemical Plant.
‫هذا المصنع الشرقي للجميع‬
At night, everyone's off work and home.
‫لقد عاد الجميع إلى المنزل بعد العمل في الليل‬
There's no one left in the plant.
‫لا يوجد أحد في المصنع‬
That is my East Chemical Plant.
‫هذا مصنعي الشرقي
I hold sway over this place.
‫أنا المسؤول عن هذا المكان
So free.
كم هو حر
I'm envious, really.
أحسدك
I walk on the pipes whenever I'm free at night.
‫كنت أتجول في الممر ليلاً
There are countless pipes in our plant,
‫لدينا الكثير من الأنظار في المصنع‬
reaching every nook and cranny,
في كل مكان
making it easy to get anywhere.
من السهل الذهاب إلى أي مكان
[East Integrated Chemical Plant]
كن حذرا
Those ladders are rusty.
لقد صدمت السلالم
Don't miss a step and fall.
لا تسقط قدميك
How do you know the ladders are rusty?
‫كيف عرفت أن السلم قد صدم‬
It's been so many years
منذ سنوات عديدة
You really are a smart one.
يجب أن يكون ذكيا
What do they call people like you?
ما يسمى هذا؟
A scholar who never leaves home,
إن لم يخرج الموهوبين
yet knows everything about the world.
قبل أن يخرج من المنزل
I'm different.
أنا مختلف
People like me...
أنا
won't realize anything
يجب أن ننتظر كل شيء
until the eleventh hour,
تأخر نهاية الخريف
until it's right in front of my face.
قبل أن يحين الوقت
What's wrong with you?
ماذا بك
Nothing.
لا شيء
I just wander around at night when I'm free.
أنا فقط أتجول في المساء
Just roam around. But sometimes,
التجول بشكل عشوائي ولكن أحيانا
I keep walking
عندما تمشي
and end up reaching Xiaodan's place.
ربما ذهبت إلى منزل شياو دان
Since I'm already there,
لقد وصلت
I'd sit on the heating pipes to keep her company.
سأبقى معها في الأنبوب الدافئة
But the pipes are so close to her house
‫لكن هذا الأنبوب قريب جداً
that I can hear Chief Engineer Yan talking inside.
‫يمكنني سماع كلام العمال يان في المنزل
And then?
‫وبعد ذلك
Then...
ثم
Chief Engineer Yan's transfer order has been issued.
‫أمر نقل العمال يان
He's going back to Shanghai.
سيعود إلى شنغهاي
Xiaodan is supposed to move back
يجب أن تنتهي شياو دان من امتحان القبول الجامعي
So this time, they'll go back to Shanghai
لم يعودوا إلى شنغهاي لزيارة الأقارب فقط
Xiaodan... Xiaodan is going back to Shanghai.
شياو دان شياو دان عادت إلى شنغهاي
And you,
أنت
you're off to college.
يجب أن تذهب إلى الجامعة مرة أخرى
I'll be the only one left.
أنا الوحيد
You...
أنت
Don't be so pessimistic.
لا تكن متشائمًا
You've still got Dongdong.
أليس هناك دونغ دونغ؟
Don't be down.
لا تتشائم
Who says going to college is the only way
‫من قال إن الاختبار الجامعي فقط‬
to get out of the East Chemical Plant?
‫يمكن الخروج من مصنع دونغ هوا‬
You can also get a job out of town in the future.
‫يمكنك أيضًا الذهاب إلى مكان آخر للعمل‬
Y-You're going to college.
أنت أنت في الجامعة
Have you decided where to apply?
هل فكرت في مكان الاختبار
Is it far away?
هل هو بعيد؟
I also have no idea.
لا أعرف أيضا
I don't know where these tracks
لا أعرف إلى أين
will lead me, either.
إلى أين يمكن أن يأخذني
Haven't you ever thought about going out to see the world?
ألم تفكر في الخروج؟
No, I haven't.
لم أفكر في ذلك
I think our plant is great.
أعتقد أن مصنعنا جيد
Right? It's comfortable.
أليس كذلك؟ كم هو مريح
Besides,
علاوة على ذلك
no matter how fast or far a train runs,
‫مهما استطاع القطار الركض بسرعة
it goes out along the tracks,
‫هرب من هذا الممر الحديدي
and it has to come back sooner or later,
سيعود عاجلاً أم آجلاً
right?
أليس كذلك
Won't you guys come back after you go off
لماذا خرجتم إلى الجامعة
to college?
ولم تعودوا
You mean, after graduation?
إذا تخرجت
If I'm not working at the plant,
إذا لم يكن في المصنع
I-I wouldn't know what to do back here.
لا أعرف لماذا عدت
Your dad, right?
والدك، أليس كذلك؟
Mr. Ding.
العم دينغ
And all the other uncles of yours.
و عمك والرجال
They've spent their whole lives at the plant.
لقد بقى في المصنع طوال حياته
Isn't that fine? What's wrong with that?
أليس هذا جيدًا؟ ماذا حدث؟
Everyone knows everyone else inside out.
الجميع يعرفون جيدا أليس كذلك
If anyone runs into any problems,
إذا حدث أي شيء
they call for help, and everyone will respond.
يصرخ كلهم
Everyone will come to help.
جاء الجميع للمساعدة
How great it is!
هذا رائع
Where else can you find that kind of atmosphere?
أين يمكنني العثور على هذا الجو
My mom says
قالت أمي
some people are just sheltering from the rain at the station.
بعض الناس يتجنبون المطر في محطة القطار
Some
بعض الناس
leave in private cars.
سيركبون سيارة خاصة
leave on the bus.
سيركبون الحافلة
And some just stay where they are.
بعض الناس سيبقون في مكانهم
I'll miss you, too.
لا أريد أن أتركك
Actually, what my mom says isn't
في الواقع ما قالته أمي
necessarily right.
ليس بالضرورة صحيحة
I think as long as we work hard,
أعتقد أنه طالما نعمل بجد
we can all stay on the same train.
يمكننا أن نكون في نفس السيارة
So, don't give up, Xiaoman.
لذلك لا تستسلم يا شياو مان
Xiaoman, let's go. Xiaoman.
لنذهب يا شياو مان
Zhang Xiaoman, why aren't you answering?
تشانغ شياو مان لماذا لا توافق
Didn't we agree to go to the sports school today?
ألم نتفق على الذهاب إلى المدرسة الرياضية اليوم؟
I've got it in my heart.
كنت أفكر
I was just planning to go look for you.
كنت أريد أن أبحث عنك
-Yet I fell asleep while lying down. -Hurry up.
لقد نمت قليلاً أسرع
I have to get home before my dad gets off work.
يجب أن أعود إلى المنزل قبل أن ينتهي من العمل
Coming.
أنا قادم
Sir, I really don't need to do it?
لا داعي لذلك يا أستاذ
You really don't. Listen to me, Xiaoman.
لا داعي حقاً استمعي لي يا شياو مان
Go on, Xiaoman.
اذهبي يا شياو مان
How was it?
ما رأيك؟
Wasn't it just a physical test?
أليست مجرد اختبار رياضي؟
Why did it take so long?
لماذا استغرقت وقتاً طويلاً؟
Well,
لا
they got a student to fight me.
وجدت طالبًا يقاتلني
They were so rough.
إنهم لا يفعلون شيئاً خطيراً
Did you get hurt?
هل تأذيت؟
I'm fine. I was wearing protective gear.
‫لا بأس يوجد معدات‬
What did the teacher say to you just now?
ماذا قال لك المعلم للتو؟
He told me not to bother thinking about junior college.
قال لي ألا أفكر في الجامعة
W-What does he mean?
ماذا؟ ماذا يعني عدم التفكير؟
H-How could he say that?
لماذا قال ذلك؟
I think he makes a good point.
أعتقد أن كلامه منطقي
I don't think so.
لا أعتقد ذلك
L-Let's ignore him.
دعينا لا نهتم به
We'll turn to another... another teacher.
لنبحث عن معلم آخر
Someone with good judgment.
‫ابحث عن شخص ذكي
Why should we listen to him?
لماذا هو يقول ما هو
No, he asked me to go straight for the sports academy.
‏لا، طلب مني دخول كلية الرياضة‏
I knew you were the best.
كنت أعلم أنك الأفضل
I don't want to go back to the plant.
لا أريد العودة إلى المصنع
I want to stay here for a while.
أريد البقاء هنا لبعض الوقت
Stay for a while?
بعد قليل
Okay! Then let's stay here for a while.
حسناً ابقي قليلاً
Xiaoman.
شياو مان
I've been giving thought to the college entrance exam lately.
كنت أفكر في امتحان الجامعة مؤخرًا
I was wondering
كنت أفكر
how to turn a hobby into a career.
كيف يمكن تحويل هواياتي إلى مهنة
I'm not good at math
الرياضيات ليست جيدة
or algebra.
‫الجيل غير جيد
I'm no good at geometry either.
لا يمكن
But I'm good at drawing.
لكنني ماهرة في الرسم
So I wondered
كنت أفكر
how to make a career out of it.
كيف يمكن تحويل الرسم إلى مهنة
Then I realized
ثم فكرت
I could go for the architectural design major.
يمكنني أن أذهب للاختبار في تصميم البناء
I-I could go to Shanghai
‫سأذهب إلى شانغهاي
and apply to the Tongzhou University.
‫ثم سنختبر في نفس الاسرة
How about you try to enroll at a college in Shanghai, too? We could be together.
‏ما رأيك أن تذهب إلى (هاي)؟‏
Are you applying to Tongzhou
‫هل دخلت في نفس الاسرة بسبب‬
because it's in Shanghai?
‫هل تونغ تشو في شنغهاي‬
Of course not.
بالطبع لا
It's because Tongzhou has the best architecture program.
لأن قسم البناء في تونغتشو هو الأفضل
You don't want to go to Shanghai?
‫لا تريد الذهاب إلى شنغهاي
It's not like that.
لا
I know your family is moving to Shanghai.
أعلم أن عائلتك ستنتقل إلى شنغهاي
I didn't actually want to go.
في الواقع لا أريد الذهاب
But as you know,
لكنك تعلم
I can't change my dad's decisions.
لا يمكنني تغييره
I definitely want to stay with you.
بالتأكيد أريد أن أكون معك
I want to be together with you wherever we go.
سنكون معًا مهما ذهبنا في المستقبل
And I didn't know how to tell you.
ولا أعرف كيف أخبرك
I thought I'd wait until after the college entrance exam.
كنت أفكر ما رأيك أن نتحدث بعد امتحان القبول الجامعي
We could just enjoy our time together in these few months.
سنبقى معا في هذه الأشهر
But you knew all along.
اتضح أنك تعرف كل شيء
Chief Engineer Yan, what brings you here?
‫أيها المدير يان لماذا أتيت
Go easy on the chili.
‫ضعي القليل من الفلفل الحار
Our family likes chili.
يمكن أن نأكل الحار في منزلنا
Mrs. Liu, going to buy groceries?
‫سيدة ليو، لنذهب لشراء الخضروات
Yeah.
لنذهب لشراء الخضروات
Xiaoman.
شياو مان
Welcome, Chief Engineer Yan!
المدير يان هنا
What brings you here?
لماذا أنت هنا
Here, come on inside and have a seat.
تفضل بالدخول
No need to go inside.
لا داعي للدخول
My wife cooked a few Shanghai dishes
لقد طبخت عمتك بعض الأطباق في شنغهاي
and asked me to bring them to you.
طلبت مني أن أحضر لك
She wanted you to have a taste.
وقال لك أن تتذوقه
That's great.
هذا رائع
She's so good at cooking!
عمتي تطبخ لذيذة جدا
Last time Xiaodan brought over some steamed buns,
أحضرت الكعك الكبير شياو دان
I gobbled them all up.
أكلتها كلها
-Have a seat, please. -I'm glad you like them.
تفضل بالجلوس تفضل بالجلوس
Here.
تعال
Oh, God. Doing the big washing?
يا لك من فتى جيد   غسل كبير
Yeah.
نعم
My school uniform got dirty.
أزياء المدرسة محجورة
Haven't washed it in ages.
لم أغسله منذ وقت طويل
Let me put this inside.
ضعه في الداخل
Speaking of this courtyard,
هذا الفناء
I haven't been here for more than a decade.
لقد جئت إلى هنا منذ أكثر من عشر سنوات
It hasn't changed a bit.
ما زلت هكذا
Yeah. We were assigned an apartment back then.
‫نعم، لقد قامت بتقسيم الغرفة لعائلتي
But my grandma didn't want to leave.
إذًا جدتي لا تحب الرحيل
She just loved this place.
إنها تحب هذا المكان
So we didn't move and just stayed here.
لذلك لم تنتقل لذلك بقيت
Old people never like to move.
لا يحب العجوز الانتقال
Well,
‫حسناً
Chief Engineer Yan, did you come to see me about something?
‫سيد يان هل تبحث عني
It's fine. I just want to have a chat with you.
.لا شيء، سأتحدث معك
Chief Engineer Yan, I took Xiaodan to Beijing this time.
أيها المدير يان، هذه المرة أحضرت شياو دان إلى بكين
It was indeed us... messing around.
‫هذا صحيح
The families must have been worried.
ألا تشعرين بالقلق؟
-We two… -Let's not talk about this.
لا نتحدث عن هذا
We just decided and left.
سنغادر
It's fine. Sit, sit down.
لا بأس اجلسي
Where did you two go for fun in Beijing?
أين تلعبان في بكين
We didn't do anything fun.
لم نلعب أي شيء
We just w-went there for the competition
ذهبت إلى هناك للمشاركة في المسابقة
and came back right after.
سأعود بعد الانتهاء
But the train ride back and forth took a really long time.
لكن القطار مر وقت طويل
What a wasted trip.
ذهب هباء
There are so many fun places in Beijing.
هناك الكثير من الأماكن الممتعة في بكين
The Great Wall, the Yihe Garden,
مدينة طويلة   حديقة يي خه
the Forbidden City, the Temple of Heaven,
القصر الملكي
right? And the Temple of Earth.
أليس كذلك؟
Yeah, we wanted to go.
نعم أريد الذهاب
But we didn't have time during this trip.
ليس لدي وقت هذه المرة
You can go next time when you have the chance.
سنجد فرصة أخرى في المستقبل
Time was indeed tight.
الوقت ضيق بالفعل
You know, for you guys,
أنتم
the college entrance exam is only in a few months.
امتحان القبول الجامعي بعد بضعة أشهر
It's the same for both of you.
أنتما متشابهان
Especially Xiaodan,
خاصة شياو دان
she must focus on her studies.
يجب التركيز على الدراسة
Well,
هذا
there are way too many distractions for her right now.
الآن هناك الكثير من الأشياء التي تجعلها منزعجة
Let me name a few examples.
على سبيل المثال
Like this competition,
مثل هذه المسابقة
right?
أليس كذلك
Chief Engineer Yan.
المدير يان
This was a legitimate competition.
هذه المسابقة مباراة رسمية
It was organized by... by...
إنها
the Institute of Broadcasting.
من كلية البث
There were hosts all over there.
كلها من المقدم
We checked it out.
لقد ذهبنا جميعا
It means nothing.
لا فائدة
And for another example,
على سبيل المثال
your influence on her.
تأثيرك لها
Xiaodan... Regarding Xiaodan's studies,
شياو دان وشياو دان
although I can't help much,
على الرغم من أنني لا أستطيع المساعدة
I haven't affected her studies.
لكنني لم أؤثر على دراستها
About this competition,
في هذه المباراة
it's actually just a dream.
هي حلم
I... I wanted to take her to fulfill it,
أريد أن آخذها إلى هناك
so she won't regret it in the future.
لا تندم بعد ذلك
I didn't think too much about it.
لم أفكر كثيرا
I know you care about her.
أعلم أنك تعاملها بشكل جيد
Let me be straight with you.
سأقول بصراحة
In these days before the college entrance exam,
قبل امتحان القبول الجامعي
I hope you can help her
بصفتك صديقها
as her friend.
آمل أن تساعدها
As for how to help...
كيف؟
I think you should understand what I mean.
أعتقد أنك تفهم قصدي
I know, I know.
أعرف أعرف
Well,
حسناً
do not affect Xiaodan's studies,
لا تؤثر على دراسة شياو دان
and do not distract her.
لا تجعلها تشتت
Um,
هذا
she needs to get a good score on the college entrance exam
يجب أن نجعلها تحصل على نتيجة جيدة في امتحان القبول الجامعي
and get into a good university.
وتدرس بجامعة جيدة
I... I know.
أنا أعرف
Keep my distance.
حافظ على المسافة
It's a deal.
اتفقنا
Listen, Xiaoman.
أقول لك يا شياو مان
You're not 18 yet,
على الرغم من أنك لست في الثامنة عشر
but I see you
لكن في قلبي
as a real man.
أعتبرك رجلا
You know I like you very much.
أنت تعرف أنني أحبك كثيرا
So I think we had a good talk today.
لذلك أعتقد أن الحديث جيد اليوم
It was a good man-to-man talk.
هذه محادثة بين رجل جيد
Right?
صحيح؟
Of course,
بالطبع
since it's between men,
لا أريد أن أعرف
I don't want Xiaodan to know about it.
لا أريدها أن تعرف
Okay?
حسناً
I u-understand.
‏فهمت‏
After the college entrance exam, well,
بعد امتحان القبول الجامعي، أليس كذلك؟
you're welcome at our place anytime.
مرحبًا بك في المنزل في أي وقت
You two can have all the fun you want
كما تشائين
As for the future and the path ahead,
أما بالنسبة للمستقبل، الطريق المستقبلي، أليس كذلك؟
the world is boundless. I won't interfere.
لا يهمني
I understand, Mr. Yan.
فهمت يا عمي
Really?
فهمت
I'll definitely support Xiaodan
سأدعم شياو دان بالتأكيد
to do well on the college entrance exam.
‏اجتهدي في امتحان القبول الجامعي‏
I-I'll help out.
سأساعدك
Good.
حسنا
Enjoy the dishes now.
تناول هذا الطعام بسرعة
If they get cold, it won't taste right.
إذا برد هذا الطعم غير صحيح
As Shanghainese say, the flavor is gone.
قال الناس في شنغهاي إن الطعم غير جيد
Alright?
حسنا
-Okay. -You eat. I'm leaving.
حسنًا، كُلي، سأغادر الآن
Let me empty the lunch box, so you can take it back.
عمي، سآخذ صندوق الطعام
Don't bother. We'll handle it later.
لا داعي لنتحدث لاحقا
I'm off.
سأذهب
Take care, Chief Engineer Yan.
مع السلامة أيها المدير يان
Bye.
مع السلامة مع السلامة
Everyone, stay in your seats.
لا تتحركوا
The power will be back soon.
سيأتي الكهرباء بعد قليل
Forget about the power!
‫لماذا تأتي‬
I'll be the first to run! Follow me!
سأركض أولًا، اتبعوني
Don't go!
لا تذهب
Who said you could leave?
من سمح لكم بالذهاب
Why didn't you go?
لماذا لا تذهب
You also didn't go, right?
ألم تغادر أيضًا؟
Then I'm leaving now.
سأذهب الآن
Don't you want to ask...
ألا تسأل
where I'm going?
إلى أين أذهب
Where are you going?
إلى أين تذهب؟
Let's go.
هيا
Hurry! You guys are so slow.
‫أسرعوا  ركضوا ببطء
Don't push me!
لا تدفعني
Run that way!
اركض هناك
She went to the rooftop.
ذهبت إلى السطح
Sorry.
آسف
Wait for me.
انتظريني
Zhang Xiaoman!
تشانغ شياو مان
They said
قالوا
you went to the rooftop to look for me last night.
أنك ذهبت إلى السطح البارحة للبحث عني
Who said that?
من قال ذلك؟
Never mind who. Just tell me. Did you go there?
لا تهتمي، فقط أخبريني هل ذهبت أم لا
Does it matter whether I went or not?
ما المشكلة إذا ذهبت أم لا
Did... Did you wait for me?
هل تنتظرني؟
Of course not. Why would I wait for you?
بالطبع لا من ينتظرك
I'm asking you.
أسألك
Did you go?
هل ذهبت أم لا
No, I didn't.
لم أذهب
You...
أنت
Just admit it if you went there
اعترف بذلك إذا ذهبت
and deny it if you didn't.
إذا لم تذهب لن تعترف
I didn't go. I really didn't.
لم أذهب لم أذهب
Just keep being stubborn.
أنت عنيد
So stubborn!
عنيد
Mom, Dad, what's the occasion today?
أبي، أمي، ما هو اليوم؟
Why are there fireworks?
ما زلت تطلق الألعاب النارية
Why was there only one?
لماذا يوجد واحدة فقط
W-What?
ماذا ماذا
You're not keeping your distance today?
لا تحافظ على المسافة اليوم
Were you home last night?
هل كنت في المنزل الليلة الماضية؟
Yes. Where else would I be?
نعم، لست في المنزل أين؟
Then did you see the fireworks?
هل رأيت الألعاب النارية؟
Yes, I did.
نعم
It was really weird.
غريب جدا
They just went off twice
ضعها مرتين فقط
and then stopped.
لن يطلق سراحه
I set them off.
أنا وضعته
You did it?
هل وضعتها؟
For me?
وضعته لي
Who else would it be for?
وإلا لمن وضعته
It was for you to see.
هذا لك
How was it?
ما رأيك؟
Is this your way of keeping me company?
هذا هو طريقة مرافقتك
Yeah. When you see fireworks,
نعم بمجرد أن ترى الألعاب النارية
you'll know I'm around.
عرفت أنني هنا
What do you think?
ما رأيك؟
I like it.
نعم
That's good.
هذا جيد
If you like it,
إذا أحببتها
then every Friday from now on,
فيما بعد كل يوم الجمعة
I'll set off fireworks for you,
سأطلق الألعاب النارية لك
so you know I'm here.
ستعرف أنني هنا
Okay. Then we have to set a time.
حسنًا، علينا تحديد موعدًا
Otherwise, I might miss it.
وإلا أخشى أن تفوت
Whatever time you say.
كم الساعة قلت كم الساعة
Then let's say 9:17.
إذًا 9:17
9:17. Okay.
9:17، حسناً
That's easy to remember.
هذا سهل
From now on, every Friday
في كل يوم الجمعة
at 9:17 PM,
الساعة 9:17 مساءً
I'll set off fireworks for you. Behold.
سأطلق الألعاب النارية لك انظر
Okay. I'll be waiting.
حسنا سأنتظر
Xiaoman.
شياو مان
Keep me company to the end.
سنرافقك إلى النهاية
Deal?
اتفقنا
"Housing reform. Are you really going to reform?"
هل حقا تريد تغيير الشقة
Look at the headline in the newspaper.
انظر إلى موضوع الصحيفة
Even they don't have a clue.
لا تعرف
Xiaodan has been behaving well recently.
أداء شياو دان جيد مؤخرًا
She doesn't even take a glance at such a good TV show.
لم أشاهد مسلسل جيد كهذا
Sweetie.
نعم.
Yang Zheng and Wen Hui are back together in the end.
"يانغ تشينغ" و"وين هوي" معاً أخيراً.
Stop it.
هل أنت متفرغ؟
Yes. They will definitely be together in the finale.
‫أجل، سينتهي الأمر معاً
What's wrong?
ما الخطب؟
Our girl is studying. What are you doing?
‏ما هذا؟‏
Who? Who is with whom?
من؟ من؟
It's "Cherish Our Love Forever,"
‫‪"‬ดำเน ع الحب إلى النهاية‪"‬‬
the TV drama I'm watching.
هل تشاهد المسلسلات التلفزيونية؟
With a mother like you, she won't do well.
أنت أمه لا يمكن أن يكون بخير
We haven't walked side by side for a long time.
لم نغادر معا منذ وقت طويل
I wish it would rain every day.
إذا تمطر كل يوم
I made an exception this time.
هذه المرة
I was worried it'd be unsafe for you to go back alone.
أخشى أن تعود بمفردك غير آمن
Go back.
عودي
Bye.
لنذهب
Get him!
اضربوه
Beat him!
اقتلوه
Learn your lesson.
تذكر
Use this to hit him! Break his arm!
اضرب هذا  خصم يدك
Hit him!
اضرب
Xiaoman!
شياو مان
Smash him to pieces!
اقتلوه
Boss!
سيدي
Xiaodan!
شياو دان
Don't come over!
لا تقترب
Let go of me! Let go!
اتركني اتركني
Let me go!
اتركني
Do you want to die?
هل تريد الموت؟
Xiaodan, run!
شياو دان، اذهب
Run!
هيا
-Boss!
أيها الرئيس أيها الرئيس
Bro! Bro!
أخي أخي
Are you okay?
هل أنت بخير؟
Bro, wake up! Bro!
أخي استيقظ أخي
Bro!
أخي
Xiaodan, regarding what happened tonight,
شياو دان
if anyone asks,
إذا سأل أحد
say nothing. I'll handle it.
لا تقل أي شيء سأتولى الأمر
Come over here.
تعال تعال
You guys, come here.
تعالوا تعالوا
What happened to you?
ما خطبك؟
-Come here! Come! -What's your name?
تعال إلى هنا ما اسمك
What happened to your face?
ماذا حدث لوجهك؟
What's your name?
ما اسمك
From which district?
أي منطقة؟
Come on, let me see.
دعني أرى
Where are you going?
إلى أين تذهبون
Which district are you from?
أي منطقة؟
Xiaoman.
‫شياو مان
You didn't sleep last night?
ألم تنامي الليلة الماضية؟
What's wrong with you?
ما بك
What's up?
ماذا حدث
Did you not do your homework?
ألم تكتب الواجبات؟
Xiaoman.
شياو مان
Don't mess with me.
لا تضربني
Who beat you up?
من ضربك؟
What're you yelling about?
لماذا تصرخ؟
Come on, tell me who hit you.
لا أخبرني من ضربه
No one. Nobody beat me up.
لا
I was boxing.
قتال مع الآخرين
It got intense, and I lost.
لقد كنت مستعجلاً ولم ألعب من قبل
They are professionals.
إنهم محترفون
There's no way you can beat them.
هل يمكنك هزيمتهم؟
Come on.
تعال تعال
What are you doing here?
لماذا أنت هنا
Does your face still hurt?
هل ما زال وجهك يؤلمك؟
It's scabbing over.
‏أنت مصاب‏
Don't wait for me after school.
لا تنتظرني بعد المدرسة
I've got a new job.
وجدت عمل جديد
We don't go the same way.
ليس نفس الطريق
Why did you get a new job again?
لماذا تبحث عن عمل جديد
Aren't you going to apply to a sports school?
‏ألا تريدين دخول مدرسة الرياضة؟‏
Listen,
‏اسمعي‏
you still need to prepare for your academic subjects.
يجب أن نستعد درس الثقافة
You can't skip that.
لا يمكن ألا نستعد
I know. Don't worry about it.
أعلم لا تقلق
Did you hear that?
هل سمعت
Did you hear the big news?
هل سمعت الأخبار الهامة؟
Feng Xiaobo was beaten to death.
قتل فنغ شياو بو
Beaten to death?
نعم
Beaten to death.
‫ضرب حتى الموت‬
There are assorted versions now.
الآن كل النسخة التي تقول
The rumors are wild.
انتشر بشكل غريب
Some say he was hit in the back of the head with an iron rod.
‫قال أحدهم إن العصا الحديدية قتلت في الرأس‬
Some say he was stabbed to death.
‫قال أحدهم أنه طعن بالسكين‬
Others say
أحدهم قال
Feng Xiaobo was killed by a single punch.
ضرب فينج شياو بو بلكمة واحدة
Killed by one punch.
ضرب حتى الموت
There are various versions.
كل نسخة
Feng Xiaobo was a bad guy,
شخصية فنغ شياو بو ليست جيدة
but he didn't deserve to be beaten to death.
لكن ليس من الضرب حتى الموت
He was a terrible person.
إنه سيء للغاية
Who held such a grudge against him?
من لديه مثل هذا الكراهية الكبيرة
I'll ask around for you
سأسألك لاحقا
and try to figure it out.
اسأل
Do you know?
هل تعرف
No, I don't.
لا
He's fine.
إنه بخير
Feng Xiaobo deserved it.
تستحق فنغ شياو بو
-That was what he got for being a bully. -Xiaoman.
لا تدعه يتنمر على الآخرين، شياو مان
Ms. Tong.
أستاذ تونغ
Come with me.
تعال إلى هنا
What's wrong?
ماذا حدث
Nothing.
لا بأس
Xiaoman, let's go.
لنذهب يا شياو مان
Oh, no.
انتهى أمرنا انتهى أمرنا
Xiaoman threw that punch.
تلك اللكمة ضربتها شياو مان
Don't talk nonsense. What are you talking about?
لا تتفوه بالهراء
Get the ball.
الكرة
Oh, no.
انتهى الأمر
Talk properly.
تكلم بشكل جيد
The police are inside.
الشرطة بالداخل
Zhang Xiaoman.
تشانغ شياو مان
You should know why I'm looking for you, right?
يجب أن تعرف لماذا أبحث عنك
I know... I know.
أعلم أعلم
I hit Feng Xiaobo.
أنا من ضربت فنغ شياو بو
Director Hou.
سيد هو
Zhang Xiaoman is suspected of intentional assault.
‫تشانغ شياو مان مشتبه به بإيذاء شخص متعمد
I must take him back for investigation today.
يجب أن أعيده للتحقيق اليوم
We failed to educate him well.
نحن لم نعلمه جيدا
Sorry for the trouble.
آسف لإزعاجكم.
[Detention Certificate]
انظر بوضوح
Chen.
تشين
Officers,
أيها الشرطي
Xiaoman is a good kid.
شياو مان فتاة جيدة
He couldn't have hurt anyone.
لن يؤذي أحد
We will investigate thoroughly.
سنحقق في الأمر بوضوح
Let's go.
لنذهب
Xiaoman.
شياو مان
Tell the truth when you get there!
يجب أن تكون صادقاً
Isn't that Zhang Xiaoman?
أليس هذا تشانغ شياو مان؟
Zhang Xiaoman was taken away by the police!
تم القبض على تشانغ شياو مان من قبل الشرطة
Come on!
بسرعة
Isn't that Zhang Xiaoman?
أليس هذا تشانغ شياو مان؟
-Is that Zhang Xiaoman? -It really is Zhang Xiaoman!
‫تشانغ شياو مان حقاً تشانغ شياو مان
Xiaoman!
شياو مان
Xiaoman! Xiaoman!
شياو مان شياو مان
Xiaoman!
‫شياو مان
Xiaoman!
شياو مان
Sweetie, don't cry.
لا تبكي
What happened?
ماذا حدث؟
Xiaoman may look like a good kid,
شياو مان تبدو جيدة
but he always hangs out with ruffians.
‫يتسكع مع شخص غير عادي
Mom, can you not say that?
أمي، هل يمكنك ألا تقولي هذا؟
He was just trying to protect me.
أليس من أجل حمايتي؟
Were it not for Xiaoman,
لولا شياو مان
-last night... -Enough.
الليلة الماضية -حسناً -
Stop talking about it.
لا تتكلمي لا تتكلمي
Do you know if word gets out,
هل تعرف ماذا سيحدث
what people will say?
ماذا يقولون؟
Don't say another word, Sweetie.
توقف عن الكلام
Hello? Who is this?
ألو من أنت
I see. Thank you.
فهمت شكرا
So what's the situation?
كيف حالك أيها العجوز؟
He's not dead,
لم يمت
but it's unclear how bad the injuries are.
لكن لا نعرف كيف أصيب الآن
Then Dad, what about Xiaoman?
ماذا عن شياو مان؟
He won't be in big trouble, will he?
هل ستكون شياو مان بخير؟
Hard to say.
من الصعب القول
Although the other guy started the fight,
على الرغم من أن الطرف الآخر هو من بدأ
and Xiaoman was forced to fight back,
لقد أجبرت شياو مان على فعل ذلك
he did injure that guy, after all.
لكنه جرح
In the end, it's up to the police
في النهاية يجب أن يكون آلية الأمن العام
to decide how to classify the case.
لنرى كيف يقرر
"How to classify the case"?
ماذا تقصد بالتحديد
What else could it be?
كيف يمكنني أن أقرر؟
Didn't Xiaoman hit him
ألم تضرب شياو مان
in order to protect me?
من أجل حمايتي؟
Why can't they classify that? Just decide...
ماذا لا يمكن أن يقرر
I'm going...
سأذهب
I-I have to go to the police station to testify.
يجب أن أذهب إلى مكتب الأمن العام لأشهد
I'm going to testify at the police station.
سأشهد مكتب الأمن العام
What are you going for? What for?
ماذا تفعل
I'm going to testify!
سأذهب لأشهد
Xiaoman can explain it to the police himself.
سأشرح للشرطة بنفسي
It's no use for you to go.
لا فائدة من الذهاب
Nobody has died,
لم يمت أحد بعد
but the rumors say someone did.
لقد انتشرت إلى شخص ميت
If people say you were harassed by those hooligans,
إذا قال الناس أنك تعرضت للتنمر عليك
what will you do then?
ماذا سنفعل
I don't care about that!
لا أهتم بهذه الأشياء
Does it matter?
لا يهم
Xiaoman is already under detention!
لقد دخلت شياو مان
You are a girl!
أنت فتاة
He is a boy.
إنه فتى
It's different.
مختلف
Come back. Get inside quickly.
ارجع ارجع ادخل بسرعة
-Enough! -Come in.
حسنا ادخل
I'm going to the police station.
سأذهب إلى مكتب الأمن العام
Don't worry.
لا تقلق
I will report the facts you told me
سأعلن الحقيقة التي قلتها
to the police in full detail.
إلى آلية الأمن العام
We'll try not to let Xiaoman be wronged, okay?
لنحاول ألا تدع شياو مان مظلوم
Stay home and watch her.
راقبها في المنزل
Don't let her go anywhere.
لا تذهب إلى أي مكان
Be good.
كوني مطيعة
Sweetie, I know you're anxious.
‏أعرف أنك قلقة‏
But there's no point in you going.
لكن لا فائدة من الذهاب
Right? You're just a child.
أليس كذلك أنت طفل
Going there won't help.
لا فائدة من الذهاب
Okay?
حسنا
Come on. Come inside.
تعال تعال ادخل
Alright, come in, Sweetie.
حسنًا، لقد دخلت